Beth: Seeking a diagnosis of Autism
spectrum disorder, can be helpful as
it can give a better understanding
of why a person behaves the way
they do and why they always may have
felt different, therefore working
to increase their confidence.
Joe: It can give parents and their
child a clear sense of the limitations
and challenges they may face as a
result of the disorder, and help
gain more understanding regarding
behaviour, strengths, needs and
the appropriate support available.
It can help parents feel more able
to cope with the reactions of others
to their child and have confidence
in explaining their behaviour, and
helping them understand that their
child is not just being difficult.
Beth: A diagnosis can also help gain
the correct support in all areas,
especially financially if needed, and
in educational settings at all levels.
However, support in school is not solely
dependent on a diagnosis, but is based
on individual needs, and some families
may be entitled to benefits such as DLA
if their disability impacts their ability
to function at home or in the community.
Joe: If a parent wants a diagnosis and
the child or young person is old enough
and has the capacity to comprehend the
process, they should be involved in
the decision making where possible.
What needs to be remembered is that
every person is different whether
diagnosed with a disorder or not,
and it is important to consider the
implications to the people involved, not
just in the present but for the future..